The ability of python to allow you
to use broadcasting operations and
Python的特性允许你使用广播(broadcasting )功能
more generally, the great flexibility of
the python numpy program language is,
这是python的numpy程序语言库中最灵活的地方
I think, both a strength as well as
a weakness of the programming language.
而我认为这是程序语言的优点 也是缺点
I think it's a strength because
they create expressivity of the language.
优点的原因在于它们创造出语言的表达性
A great flexibility of the language lets
you get a lot done even with just a single
python语言巨大的灵活性 使得你仅仅通过一行代码
line of code.
就能做很多事情
But there's also weakness because with
broadcasting and this great amount of
但是这也是缺点 由于广播巨大的灵活性
flexibility, sometimes it's possible
you can introduce very subtle bugs or
有时候如果你对于广播的特点
very strange looking bugs, if you're not
familiar with all of the intricacies of
以及广播的工作原理这些细节不熟悉的话
how broadcasting and how features like broadcasting work.
你可能会产生很细微或者看起来很奇怪的bug
For example, if you take a column vector
and add it to a row vector, you would
例如 如果你将一个列向量添加到一个行向量当中
expect it to throw up a dimension mismatch or type error or something.
你会以为它报出维度不匹配或类型错误之类的错误
But you might actually get back
a matrix as a sum of a row vector and
但是实际上你会得到一个
a column vector.
行向量和列向量的求和
So there is an internal logic to these strange effects of Python.
在python的这些奇怪的影响之中 有一个内在的逻辑关系
But if you're not familiar with Python,
I've seen some students have very strange,
但是如果你对python不熟悉 我曾经见过一些学生
very hard to find bugs.
非常生硬 非常艰难地去寻找bug
So what I want to do in this video is
share with you some couple tips and
所以我在这里想做的就是分享给你们一些技巧
tricks that have been very
useful for me to eliminate or
这些技巧对我非常有用 它们能
simplify all the strange looking bugs in my own code.
消除或者简化在我的代码中所有看起来很奇怪的bug
And I hope that with these tips and tricks,
同时我也希望通过这些技巧
you'll also be able to much more easily
write bug-free, python and numpy code.
你也能更容易地写没有bug的python和numpy代码
To illustrate one of the less intuitive effects of Python-Numpy,
为了演示Python-numpy的一个容易被忽略的效果
especially how you construct vectors in
Python-Numpy, let me do a quick demo.
特别是怎样在Python-Numpy中构造向量 让我来做一个快速示范
Let's set a = np.random.randn(5),
首先设置 a = np.random.randn(5)
so this creates five random Gaussian
这样会生成存储在数组a中的
variables stored in array a.
5个高斯随机数变量
And so let's print(a) and now it turns out that
之后输出a 从屏幕上可以得知
the shape of a when you do this
is this five comma structure.
此时a的shape(形状)是一个(5，)的结构
And so this is called a rank one array in Python and
这在python当中被称作 一个一维数组
it's neither a row vector nor a column vector.
它既不是一个行向量也不是一个列向量
And this leads it to have some
slightly non-intuitive effects.
这也导致它有一些不是很直观的效果
So for example, if I print a transpose,
it ends up looking the same as a.
举个例子,如果我输出一个转置阵 最终结果它会和a看起来一样
So a and a transpose end up looking the same.
所以a和a的转置阵最结果看起来一样
And if I print the inner product between
a and a transpose, you might think
而如果我输出a和a的转置阵的内积 你可能会想
a times a transpose is maybe the outer
product should give you matrix maybe.
a乘以a的转置返回给你的可能会是一个矩阵
But if I do that,
you instead get back a number.
但是如果我这样做 你只会得到一个数
So what I would recommend is that
when you're coding neural networks,
所以我建议当你编写神经网络时
that you just not use data structures
where the shape is 5, or n, rank 1 array.
不要在它的shape是(5, )还是(n, ) 或者一维数组时使用数据结构
Instead, if you set a to be this, (5,1),
相反 如果你设置a为(5,1)
then this commits a to
be (5,1) column vector.
那么这就将a置于5行1列向量中
And whereas previously, a and
a transpose looked the same,
而在先前的操作里 a和a的转置看起来一样
it becomes now a transpose,
now a transpose is a row vector.
而现在这样的a 变成一个新的a的转置 并且它是一个行向量
Notice one subtle difference.
请注意一个细微的差别
In this data structure, there are two
square brackets when we print a transpose.
在这种数据结构中 当我们输出a的转置时有两对方括号
Whereas previously,
there was one square bracket.
而之前只有一对方括号
So that's the difference
between this is really a 1 by
所以这就是1行5列的矩阵
5 matrix versus one of
these rank 1 arrays.
和一维数组的差别
And if you print, say,
the product between a and a transpose,
如果你输出a和a的转置的乘积
then this gives you the outer
product of a vector, right?
然后返回给你一个向量的外积 对吗?
And so, the outer product of
a vector gives you a matrix.
所以这两个向量的外积返回给你一个矩阵
So, let's look in greater detail
at what we just saw here.
就我们刚才看到的 再进一步说明
The first command that we ran,
just now, was this.
首先我们刚刚运行的命令是这个
And this created a data structure with
而且它生成了一个数据结构(a.shape)
a.shape was this funny thing (5,) so
a.shape是(5,) 一个有趣的东西
this is called a rank 1 array.
这被称作a的一维数组
And this is a very funny data structure.
同时这也是一个非常有趣的数据结构
It doesn't behave consistently as either
a row vector nor a column vector,
它不像行向量和列向量那样表现地很一致
which makes some of its effects nonintuitive.
这也让它的一些影响不那么明显
So what I'm going to recommend is that
when you're doing your programing
所以我建议 当你在
exercises, or in fact when you're
implementing logistic regression or
编程练习或者在执行逻辑回归和
neural networks that you just
do not use these rank 1 arrays.
神经网络时你不需要使用这些一维数组
Instead, if every time
you create an array,
相反 如果你每次创建一个数组
you commit to making it
either a column vector, so
你都得让它成为一个列向量
this creates a (5,1) vector, or
commit to making it a row vector,
产生一个(5,1)向量 或者你让它成为一个行向量
then the behavior of your vectors
may be easier to understand.
那么你的向量的行为可能会更容易被理解
So in this case,
a.shape is going to be equal to 5,1.
所以在这种情况下 a.shape等同于5,1
And so this behaves a lot like a, but
in fact, this is a column vector.
这种表现很像a 但是实际上却是一个列向量
And that's why you can think of this as
(5,1) matrix, where it's a column vector.
同时这也是为什么当它是一个列向量的时候你能认为这是矩阵(5,1)
And here a.shape is going to be 1,5,
同时这里a.shape将要变成1,5
and this behaves consistently
as a row vector.
这就像行向量一样
So when you need a vector,
I would say either use this or this, but
所以当你需要一个向量时 我会说用这个或那个
not a rank 1 array.
但绝不会是一维数组
One more thing that I do a lot in my
code is if I'm not entirely sure what's
我写代码时还有一件经常做的事 那就是如果我不完全确定
the dimension of one of my vectors,
I'll often throw in an assertion statement
一个向量的维度(dimension) 我经常会扔进一个断言语句
like this, to make sure, in this case,
that this is a (5,1) vector.
像这样 去确保在这种情况下是一个(5,1)向量
So this is a column vector.
或者说这是一个列向量
These assertions are really
Set to execute, and
这些断言语句实际上是要去执行的
they also help to serve as
documentation for your code.
并且它们也会有助于为你的代码提供信息
So don't hesitate to throw in assertion
statements like this whenever you
所以不论你要做什么 不要犹豫
feel like.
直接插入断言语句
And then finally, if for some reason
you do end up with a rank 1 array,
如果你不小心 以一维数组来执行
You can reshape this, a equals a.reshape
你也能够重新改变数组维数 a=a.reshape
into say a (5,1) array or a (1,5) array so
表明一个(5,1)数组或者一个(1,5)数组
that it behaves more consistently as
either column vector or row vector.
以至于它表现更像列向量或行向量
So I've sometimes seen students
end up with very hard to track
因此我有时候看见学生因为一维数组不直观的影响
because those are the nonintuitive
effects of rank 1 arrays.
以难以定位bug告终
By eliminating rank 1 arrays in my old
code, I think my code became simpler.
通过在原先的代码里清除一维数组 我的代码变得更加简洁
And I did not actually find it
restrictive in terms of things I could
而且实际上就我在代码中表现的事情而言
express in code.
我并没有发现它有什么限制
I just never used a rank 1 array.
我从来不使用一维数组
And so takeaways are to simplify
your code, don't use rank 1 arrays.
因此 要去简化你的代码 而且不要使用一维数组
Always use either n by one matrices,
总是使用n*1维矩阵(基本上是列向量)
basically column vectors, or one by
n matrices, or basically row vectors.
或者1*n维矩阵(基本是行向量)
Feel free to toss a lot of
insertion statements, so
这样你可以减少很多assert语句
double-check the dimensions
of your matrices and arrays.
来节省复核矩阵和数组的维数的时间
And also, don't be shy about calling the
reshape operation to make sure that your
另外 为了确保你的矩阵或向量是你所需要的维数
matrices or your vectors
are the dimension that you need it to be.
不要羞于reshape操作
So that,
总之
I hope that this set of suggestions
helps you to eliminate a cause of bugs
我希望这些建议能帮助你 解决一个python中的bug
from Python code, and makes the problem
exercise easier for you to complete.
从而使你更容易地完成练习